Guide to the Fowler Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Fowler family papers
1707-1870
MS 221
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
Correspondence (1806-1870), deeds (1707-1857) to property in Connecticut, and miscellaneous papers. The bulk of the correspondence is that of William Chauncey Fowler (1793-1881), an educator. Principal correspondents include George Sewall Boutwell, Lewis Cass, Salmon Portland Chase, Rufus Choate, Schuyler Colfax, Horace Mann, Gideon Algernon Mantell, and Truman Smith. Also in the papers is an account book (1854-1866) of Crampton and Fowler, manufacturers and farmers of Northford, Connecticut and a collection of autographs, including one of John Quincy Adams.
Fowler family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Fowler family.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Fowler Family Collection consists of one manuscript box and contains approximately 300 items. Deeds, 1707-1857 to land in Canaan, Guilford, Middletown, New Haven, North Branford and Wallingford Conn. Miscellaneous papers, 1756-1860, mainly receipts, bills, promissory notes and tax receipts. Also, a folder containing autographs of well known people, including one of John Qunicy Adams.
The correspondence dates from 1806-1870, the bulk of which was written to William Chauncey fowler (1793-1881). Among the correspondents are George Sewall Boutwell (1818-1905), Lewis Cass (1782-1866), Salmon Portland Chase (1808-1873), Rufus Choate (1799-1859), Schuyler Colfax (1823-1885), Horace Mann (1796-1859), Gideon Algernon Mantell (1790-1852), and Truman Smith (1791-1884).
There is an account book, 1854-1866 of Crampton & Fowler, manufacturers, and farmers, of Northford, Conn. Also, a book written by Samuel Miles Hopkins (1772-1837)* depicting public and private life in Waterbury, Conn. He comments on the appointment of Washington as Commander-in-Chief of the U.S. Forces, on General Ethan Allen, and on the history of the state of Connecticut.
*This book has been removed to Miscellaneous Manuscripts, Alphabetical Series, Mss 352.
Agriculture; Education; Families; Connecticut; Northford (Conn.); Account books; Autographs; Deeds; Educators; Farmers; Manufacturers; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Adams, Nehemiah, 1806-1878; Baldwin, Roger S. (Roger Sherman), 1793-1863; Boutwell, George S. (George Sewall), 1818-1905; Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866; Chase, Salmon P. (Salmon Portland), 1808-1873; Choate, Rufus, 1799-1859; Colfax, Schuyler, 1823-1885; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879; Fowler, Orin, 1791-1852; Fowler, William Chauncey, 1793-1881; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1790-1852; Owen, Robert Dale, 1801-1877; Percival, James Gates, 1795-1856; Smith, Truman, 1791-1884; Winthrop, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1809-1894; Fowler family; Crampton and Fowler
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1806-1870, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Deeds
    - 1746, 1784-1813 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1816-1835 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1845-1850 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1853-1857 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers
    - 1759, 1783-1822 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1834-1837 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1838-1839 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1840-1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1851-1853 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1854-1858 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1859-1866 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Crampton & Fowler, Manufacturers and Farmers of Northford, Ct.: Account book, 1854-1866 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Autograph collection (electrostatic copies), 1714-1886 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Record of texts for weekly sermons, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 16)